This is what a $25 million a year salary
looks like versus a $25,000
a year salary. About 20% of Americans
live on this amount of money or less.
So, let's say I make $25,000 a year.
People in this income bracket spend
about 41% of their pre-tax income on
housing. I've got about $850 for all my
housing expenses. That's nearly half my
after-tax budget. I'll definitely be
renting instead of owning a house. I
really can't afford to live downtown, so
I'm going to look in the outskirts. And
I found this place right outside the
city and it's within my budget for rent
and utilities. So, how am I going to get
to my job 20 minutes away from where I
live? And like most American cities,
there's not great public transportation
here. So, I'm going to need to have a
car. I spend about 15% of my income on
food. That includes both groceries and
eating out. A lot of people think that
this income bracket just goes to
McDonald's all of the time, but the
reality is the average order amount at
McDonald's is between $7 and $8. So,
that will not get me through the month.
That will get me through 13 days worth
of food. So, I got to go to the grocery
store. Unfortunately, in most lower
income areas in this country, there
aren't a ton of grocery stores and the
ones that are available are much less
likely to carry fresh produce or other
nutritious food. So, I'm going to see
what I can do by stocking up on beans
and rice, peanut butter and jelly,
Wonder Bread, Top Ramen, freezer meals.
For fresh options, I'll be looking at
potatoes and some of the cheaper
produce. And no eating out or rarely
occasionally on special occasions eating
out. If I do, I'll be looking at the
value menu at a fast food restaurant. To
get government assistance, I need my
savings account to be less than $2,000.
Check. My income needs to be lower than
$19,578.
And I make $25,000, so nope, I don't
qualify. Georgia's Medicaid website says
that I qualify for government help, but
even with that, I will be paying around
10% of my income on health-related
expenses like medicine, doctor visits,
getting care that isn't covered by this
government insurance. This is one of the
reasons why people in my income bracket
live around 7 years less than the
richest Americans. Laundry, internet
connection, cell phone, conservatively
that adds up to $105, not taking into
account the overcharges and hidden fees.
Like you're starting to see what's
happening here. This doesn't add up.
Entertainment, fitness, and travel just
isn't feasible. I have no emergency
savings, no rainy day fund, and live in
stress of an unexpected car repair, a
health emergency. I'm probably going to
have to join the huge number of
Americans that rely on debt to get
through the month, whether that's credit
card debt or short-term loans with high
interest rates. Maybe I'll need to move
back in with my parents or take on a
second job. Maybe I'll start driving
Uber or DoorDash. But what's clear is
that my full-time job, which pays much
more than the minimum wage, is still not
enough to make it through the month.